Hi, my name is Anna Veronika.
And in this video,
I will tell you about CatBoost,
a great linguistic library that
we are developing at Yandex.
CatBoost is an open source project,
so you are very welcome to use it.
In this video, I will first tell
you how CatBoost compares to other
gradient boosting algorithms
in terms of quality.
Then we will go into
details of the algorithm.
We will discuss main problems that
arise when using gradient boosting and
the ways we try to solve
these problems in CatBoost.
After that we will talk about some
useful features of the library and
about the most important
training parameters.
Let's start with some motivation
which I hope will make you want
to try the library on your data.
Here, you can see the comparison of
CatBoost with other openly available great
boosting libraries, LightGBM, XGBoost and
H2O on several openly available data sets.
These are data sets from computations and
data set the commonly known data set.
We've open sourced the code
of algorithms comparison, so
that you can reproduce results yourself.
As you can see,
CatBoost beats all other libraries in
terms of quality on these data sets.
These numbers are the results
of comparison of the algorithms
after parameter tuning.
Actually, and you can see that in
our benchmarks on GitHub, CatBoost,
without any parameter tuning, beats the
tuned algorithms in all cases except one
where tuned LightGBM is slightly
better than not tuned CatBoost.
This is because CatBoost is very
stable to hyper parameter changes.
Now let me outline the main problems that
can arise when using radian boosting.
In CatBoost,
we have put a lot of effort to solve them.
The first problem is that the existing
with gradient boosting libraries have
not optimal support or no support for
categorical features, a very natural
type of data that arises in many tasks.
To handle them,
you need to do advanced processing.
The second problem is that, if you train
your model with default parameters,
you usually get a very bad result.
To get the good model,
you need to do hyperparameter.
The next problem arises in
time critical applications and
it is the prediction speed.
If prediction speed is important,
then some people don't use gradient
boosting and use simple models.
The next problem is overfitting.
Gradient boosting is prone to overfitting,
which affects the resulting
quality of the model.
And the last on this list
is the training speed.
It is especially important for
large data sets when you need to wait for
hours or even days for
the training to finish.
It is important to make
training as fast as possible.
Let's start with a discussion
of categorical features.
Because the sophisticated
categorical feature support
is a major advantage of the library.
Gradient boosting is a machine learning
technique that works great for
heterogeneous data, or
data from different sources.
When working with heterogenous data,
we usually have numerical data and
categorical data.
An example, if numerical data is height,
it is a number.
And thus, its values can be
compared with each other.
Numerical data can be easily
used in decision trees.
In practice, however, when data
sets include categorical features,
which are also important for predictions.
Categorical feature is a feature
having a discrete set of values
that are not necessarily
comparable with each other.
An example for that could be user ID,
or name of a city.
The most commonly used practice for
dealing with categorical features and
gradient boosting is replacing
them with some numerical features
during the processing stage.
Let me introduce the techniques
that are used in CatBoost
to deal with categorical features.
The most widely used technique
which is usually applied to low
categorical features is One-hot encoding.
The original feature is removed, and
a new binary or
variable is added for each category.
By reading and boosting,
component coding can be done during the
pre possessing phase or during training.
However, it can be implemented more
efficiently in terms of training time,
which we've done in the library.
By default,
CatBoost uses one-hot encoding for
features with small number
of different values.
This can be controlled with
one_hot_max_size parameter.
Another way that we've implemented
is using number of appearances
of category in the data
set as a new feature.
This is a simple but powerful technique.
One more way to deal with categorical
features is to compute some statistic
using the label values of the object.
And that is the most powerful technique
in terms of resulting quality.
The simplest way is to
substitute the category with
value on the whole train data set.
This procedure leads to.
For example, if there is a single object
from the category in the whole training
data set, then the new
numerical feature value will be
equal to the label value of this example.
A straightforward way to overcome this
problem is to partition the data set
into two parts, and use one part to
only calculate the statistics, and
the second part to perform training.
This reduces over fitting, but
it also reduces the amount of data
used to train the model and
to calculate the statistics.
CatBoost uses a more efficient strategy,
which reduces overfitting and
allows to use the whole data set for
training.
Namely, we perform a random
permutation of the data set and for
each object we can get [INAUDIBLE] value
and more objects with the same category
value placed before the given
object in the permutation.
It also helps to use other statistics,
not only error target.
One more trick is to use
several permutations.
However, a straightforward
statistics computed for
several permutations
will lead to overfitting.
To use several permutations, CatBoost
train's several models simultaneously,
each of which is trained on a separate
permutation and uses this model for
tree structure selection.
Note that any combination of several
categorical features could be considered
as a new one.
For example, assume that
the task is music foundation and
we have two categorical features,
user ID and musical genre.
Some user prefer say rock music.
When we convert user ID and
musical genre to numerical features,
we lose this information.
And a combination of two
features solve this problems and
gives a new powerful feature.
However, the number of combinations
grows exponentially with the number of
categorical features in the data set, and
it is not possible to consider
all of them in the algorithm.
When constructing a new split for
the current tree, CatBoost considers
combinations in a greedy way.
Thus, it considers only
some good combinations.
CatBoost also generates combinations
of numerical and categorical features.
Let's now discuss the next major
difference between CatBoost and
other libraries.
It is the kind trees CatBoost
is using as base predictors,
although libraries use
different kind of trees.
Builds trees node by node,
eating them in a greedy fashion.
This way, you can get a deep
[INAUDIBLE] binary tree.
Also builds but it builds them layer
by layer and then prunes them.
So they cannot get very deep.
CatBoost uses symmetric trees.
The trees where all nodes on the same
layer contain the same split.
These trees are more simple predictors
which make the algorithm more stable
to overfitting.
They also make the algorithm more
stable to hyperparameter changes,
which means that training with default
parameters will give a good model, and
you can reduce the time spent
on tuning hyperparameters.
This type of trees also ask for
a very fast model predictions.
CatBoost model prediction is 30 to
60 times faster than those of and
extra boost in both single and
multithread mode.
Thus categorical data supports and
usage of symmetric trees are two
first major features of CatBoost.
We'll talk about other
features in the next video.
[SOUND]
[MUSIC]